[Music]
so what is it that is happening in 2020
what kind of a decade are we up for
what's going to be going on with the
portal during the coming year coming ten
years I think that the first thing that
I want to signal is that we are finally
ready to take on something which I have
always found to terrify and that has to
do with idea suppression now before we
get to idea suppression and how it
functions and what it is I want to take
new listeners through a very brief
description of how we would order the
world relative to the portal and its
objectives so if you will let me take
you back to the end of world war two
there's a lot of prehistory but we can't
afford to do everything so shortly after
World War Two there were two very
important events in the early 1950s
from our perspective one of which was
the unlocking of the three-dimensional
structure of DNA by Watson and Crick in
1953 and the other was the explosions of
hydrogen devices using work of Edward
Teller and Stanislaus Lum and what that
changed in the human picture because we
went from a short period where we were
dealing with atomic bombs where Duck and
Cover was a plausible solution to
dealing with hydrogen devices in which
the destructive power was really
incalculable it's the power of gods used
to power the Sun here on earth now for
my wit to my way of thinking since the
early 1950s
there has been no comparable explosion
of wisdom to go along with this newfound
power that humans have this new godlike
power so I've called this the twin
nuclei problem of cell and atom and I
think what we've had is an incredible
run of luck and I think it's the most
magical and marvelous thing but I don't
believe that we can count on
like forever and in fact given some of
the events of early 2020 taking place in
Iraq and Iran I would say that history
at the scale that we were accustomed to
it during the let's say first half of
the 20th century could start up at any
moment
and we're entirely unprepared for this
now in the story that has this major
through-line
that we've been following the next thing
that happens that's really important is
a guy named Eric de sola price starts to
calculate that science is on an
exponential trajectory and rather than
thinking that that's a great thing
he starts to understand that anything on
an exponential trajectory can't really
go on because it's going to burn itself
out and if science is the original
seedcorn if you will of technology and
technology of economics then effectively
what's going to happen in science is
going to percolate through a chain
through technology and into the economy
with a potential stagnation coming now
he started to arrive at these ideas I
think at Yale in the late 1950s it was
not well understood what he was talking
about and still I am always shocked that
the book science since Babylon which he
wrote and which discusses this issue is
so much less well known than say Thomas
Kuhn structure of scientific revolutions
for some reason this is so dispiriting
to so many people that we'd actually
don't discuss it much studying this work
led to the idea of talking about egos
that is embedded growth obligations now
embedded growth obligations are the way
in which institutions plan their future
predicated on legacies of growth and
since the period between the end of
World War two in 1945 in the early 70s
had such an unusually beautiful growth
regime many of our institutions became
predicated upon low variance technology
led
stable broadly distributed growth now
this is a world we have not seen in an
organic way since the early 1970s and
yet because it was embedded in our
institutions what we have is a world in
which the expectation is still present
in the form of an embedded growth
obligation that is the pension plans the
corporate ladders are all still built
very much around a world that has long
since vanished we have effectively
become a growth cargo cult that is once
upon a time planes used to land in the
Pacific let's say during World War two
and indigenous people looked at the air
strips and the behavior of the air
traffic controllers and they've been
mimicking those behaviors in the years
since as ritual but the planes no longer
land well in large measure our
institutions are built for a world in
which growth doesn't happen in the same
way anymore
all right what then happened was is that
a different structure which I have
termed the gated institutional narrative
came to become repurposed now the gated
institutional narrative is like an
exchange a financial exchange if you
will except it's an exchange of
information and ideas and in order to
actually participate in this particular
special conversation you need to have a
seat on the exchange that is you need to
write for an important paper like The
Wall Street Journal or you need to be a
senator or a congressman so that you can
gain access to the news media or you
need to be sitting at a news desk in any
of these situations whether you're a
professor or a reporter or a politician
if you can gain a seat inside of the
gated institutional narrative you can
attempt to converse with other people
within that particular conversation the
rest of us do not really have the same
level or kind of access to this highly
rarefied discussion and I've previously
compared this to what we would term a
promotion inside of the world of
professional wrestling
it's an agreed-upon structure in which
people off
agree to simulate dispute rather than
actually have disputes because somebody
could get really seriously injured but
they're in fact working together to
produce a an engaging and regular
product for mass consumption the problem
with this gated institutional narrative
is that in general it doesn't contain
the most important ideas and that is
where the gating function comes in the
most important ideas are likely to be
the ideas that are most disruptive what
if the entire food pyramid for example
was wildly off what if fats were not the
great danger we thought they were
and those waving fields of wheat that
are fabled in American song in fact give
rise to carbs which are very dangerous
to us all so if everything were inverted
let's say we're in a world where instead
of banishing volatility during the
so-called Great Moderation before 2008
we were actually building the tinder for
the world's largest financial forest
fire what if in fact we had all sorts of
things exactly backwards and completely
wrong
what if diversity wasn't always a sign
of our strength but sometimes a sign of
our weakness what if for example
immigration far from being an issue of
xenophobes versus zina files was
actually an instrument of redistribution
having very little to do with xenophobia
or Zen ophelia to begin with these sorts
of ideas can't be entertained inside of
the gated institutional narrative and
that's where the gating function comes
in what was originally a function
intended to ensure quality control of
the narrative became an instrument for
something else
and this is where I want to introduce
the most important concept that I think
we will be dealing with on a
going-forward basis in 2020 on this
program the disc
what is the disc the disc stands for the
distributed idea suppression complex now
taking it apart the center of it is idea
suppression not all ideas are good and
so idea suppression is very frequently
understood
as an important concept when we're
talking about something like bigotry or
we're talking about something like
violent ideology of course we want to
suppress certain ideas but these are not
the ideas that are principally important
inside of the disk the disk is actually
a complex it is a large collection of
different structures and it's not
controlled in any one place many of
these have emerged separately but what
makes a aspect of the disk what shows
you a particular component is that it
protects institutions from individuals
who are making valid and reasonable
points so if you imagine that the
institutions have become incredibly
fragile because they're in fact built
for growth and that plan for their
growth if it obligates them to tell
untruths and to hide certain
characteristics because they are not in
fact able to grow at the rates in which
they are supposed to you need some
complex for making sure that that
information doesn't reach the bottom
entrance to a pyramid
[Music]